so does anyone does anybody have any
ideas how to start the
discussion about the right suffering
the wrong suffering is craing to get rid
of
suffering by acting out of greed
aversion distraction right but um let's approach
distraction right but um let's approach
it through a different angle is it
uh is it the case that you start the
practice so as to get rid of suffering
as quickly as possible is that the
motivation behind starting the practice
Yeah cuz that would be quite often the
case take on taking on the practice so
that I can get rid of suffering today if
I
can but is there anything wrong with
that yeah that's the question
mhm like the Buddha teaches only one
thing he has said Dua and the ending of
Dua so someone is listening with the
intention of freeing themselves from
suffering then what's the issue with
that yeah the thing is that it's already
what we are doing by looking for Cal
pleasure we look for a way out of
suffering as quick as possible so we
engage in any other distraction or any
like sity basically so if if our
attitude toward the practice stay the
same eventually we don't we don't get
rid of it we just cover it up with some
technique method or whatever we want but
at the end we stay Within because we
don't want to face what actually Dua is
we want to get rid of it as quick as
possible so canot really give rise to
any understanding so do you see what
duka is when you start out the
practice right yeah that's what I was
going to say is like if you're you're
kind of going into it like I need to end
suffering like as fast as possible like
what you're trying to end might not
actually be what the Buddha is teaching
the end of yeah so you could basically
say um there are symptoms of the illness
and then there's the actual
illness and so you
can engage in various strategies to get
rid of the symptoms of the
illness but ironically the symptoms of
the illness are you need to experience
them in order to U diagnose properly
what the sickness is if you try to get
rid of the symptoms as quickly as
possible you won't be able to actually
understand suffering so you could even
say the practice doesn't start with
trying to get rid of suffering as
quickly as possible it starts to starts
with uh learning how
to to put it in a certain way how to
suffer properly but that doesn't mean
like seeking out the suffering in in the
sense of a self mortification neither
bodily self-mortification nor mental
self mortification it's just that uh you're
mortification it's just that uh you're
not creating that suffering it's more
like that suffering is already there
it's just that we are so trained in
avoiding it circumventing it through
various ways that we live as if it's not
there so learning how to suffer doesn't
mean making your selfs suffer it just
means recognizing the suffering that is
already there when you stop chasing as
you set sensuality acting out of un
wholesome States and so on so when you
stop that the first symptom that's going
to reveal itself is that um the tendency
where you know you've been inclining the
mind in that direction and now it wants
to keep going there and so that
discrepancy is going to be felt so
that's why practically
speaking uh taking on the practice on
the right level
means at least initially some degree of
suffering and
then um basically you
you don't uh if you just you can be sure
that if you started your practice and
then at no point in time you had to
experience any kind of at least mental
uneasiness um there's a very high at
least today you know from the starting
point that most of us come from you
would be doing it wrong yeah there's a
very high chance that your practice is
just going with the grain of the same as
you said uh just now like Tendencies of
sensuality but just in a more subtle
level so that's why the Buddha said
there are four types of practice like uh
uh painful practice with quick results
painful practice with slow results uh
Pleasant practice with quick results and
pleasant practice with slow results and
then it depends the the pleasantness of
the practice depends on what is the
intensity of the uh desire aversion and
delusion that you start with that's how
the suas Define it so most of us
virtually all of us today start with uh
intense uh quantities of lust diversion
and delusion that's why people hear
about renunciation and even in idea like
in in abstraction not even uh in um you
know in having to get themselves to
actually do it but just thinking about
it uh is already unbearable for most
people so that's a a testament to how
much uh pollution we start with and
uh pollution we start with and
accordingly then it's just um it's just
the sickness is is more serious more is
more grave so as a result of that the
symptoms that you have to put up with
while solving that sickness are most
likely going to
be more unpleasant than
not so it's like a like a cancer
so it's like a like a cancer
patient If
he if he's
basically trying to find the quickest
way to not feel displeasure on account
of the
cancer there are various kinds of mental
gymnastics that you can go that you can
achieve that goal with like you can
basically forget about it in various
ways you can distract yourself you can
uh practice you know uh
psychologisation rationalization
techniques to not acknowledge the fact
that you have cancer and that is
factually going to result in not
suffering right now but are you actually
fixing the
illness that's a thing and then um going
through the chemotherapy to put it that
way has uh unpleasant effects but if you
go through it
like it's just going to be none of the
suffering that you're go going to go
through as a result of that chemotherapy
can be compared with the suffering of
dying on account of you know
prioritizing your
present uh you
know mental uh Comfort mhm uh present mental
mental uh Comfort mhm uh present mental
comfort in favor of you know your actual
Health yeah so a certain longer term
perspective is necessary yeah
in a certain sense I'm inclined to say
that it is better to even emphasize the
future what is what is going to happen
then the present that can be that can be
something quite inauthentic in saying I
just have to be present here and now all
there is is this this present moment
that is what my meditation is about
because that can be an easy Avenue to
deny that this body is basically going
downhill even if right now you are still
healthy so the Buddha himself reflected while
so the Buddha himself reflected while
young I'm subject to old age when
healthy I'm subject to sickness while
alive I'm subject to death how how else
can you be subjected to death yeah um so
so that is what is waiting um but there
is a way out of that but not by ignoring
that future Direction yeah so that's you
you brought it up like the perfect
example of these ways to get rid of the
suffering as quickly as possible is this
like virtually most practi of today the
the direction that they revolve around
is this present moment observation and
that's essentially taking you like you
know cancer patient focusing on oh my
knees how I feel right now and the
sensations in my back and stuff all of
that to ignore the fact that he is brain
cancer and it will factually help him to
forget the fact that he might die
anytime soon and he might have a more
pleasant last two weeks of his life but
uh if he were to gain any perspective he
would see that that's not actually worth
it that's not a good deal but it does
require uh the thing is like obviously
the analogy sounds quite uh dumb like
nobody would actually do that but the
thing is when it comes to the suffering
of craving uh you don't recognize
yourself being sick in the first place
that's that's why the analogy doesn't
apply fully because if you were to see
clearly the predicament that you're in
you would be incapable of falling into
that kind of a ignorance of it you would
like as the Buddha said um there's only
two possible um results of uh
recognizing the suffering that you're
subject to one of them is uh basically
falling into vexation like lamentation
and and madness madness you could say or
uh Noble search that's right which is I
need to solve this problem there is no
other thing that
can uh come in the way of them yeah
there's nothing more important than that
yeah so whatever other problems you
thought you have up until that time
suddenly are no longer your problem but
that is because you now have inherited
one bigger problem yeah namely Your
Existence in the world yeah would you
say that another shortcoming of the
analogy is so like you talk about
chemotherapy having kind of negative
effects that's like stuff that you
wouldn't have otherwise like your hair
falling out I mean that's kind of the
one that comes to mind whereas
with trying to align yourself with the
Right View you're actually it's not
creating any new suffering it's just
kind of highlighting what's already
there that you've been facing away from
eventually you will get to recognize
that that suffering was already there
but the ignorant mind might very well
start with the wrong idea that no this
is being created by this restraint that
I'm doing now right so that's why you
might fall into the view that if I just
don't do this practice I could genuinely
be happy which is not really the case I
mean it's a relative relative sort of
it's like again the
the the happiness of of uh
prior yeah ignorance is bliss as that as
that saying goes but it's not actually
um it says that that there is the
happiness that is ignoble and there is
the happiness that is Noble yeah and of
these two obviously the noble happiness
is the foremost one yeah
yeah so practically speaking um you
can't
be you you basically have to um
relinquish the idea of what you think happiness is
the idea of what you think happiness is
you have to revise that idea let's say
um you have to recognize that anything
that you could
get unless you unless you have already
gone through a significant amount of um
The Graduate training renunciation and
authenticity authenticity and uh some
potentially tumultuous uh you know
developments um
the idea that you might have about what
happiness is is still going to be
distorted by your initial assumptions of
uh sensual pleasure and immediate
gratification so so what's the
difference between a happy mind and the
mind that is and and happiness that is
based on knowing the
Mind well uh I wanted to dedicate the
next talk to that right happiness right
suffering so um yeah so right suffering
the the thing you could say though is
that um that suffering then
um that suffering then
is
like it's not that you take it on for
some indeterminate period of time and
then you get rid of it even later it's
not it's you actually free yourself from
it by understanding it so you never find
like a kind of um
some sort of magical place where you
hide it's really you have to go through
it in it's the lack of understanding
that makes that suffering a problem like
lack of understanding makes unpleasant
feeling of any kind makes it turns it
into duka turns it into suffering that's
that sort of the the two arrows uh it
doesn't say that it's um you know it's a
person is hit by the second aror because
they haven't found some magical
um sort of a state that that protects
them from the suffering it says on
account of them not knowing the nature
of those feelings that is why they are
hit by suffering when unpleasant feeling
arises and also the unpleasant feeling
arises for the me craving for it and
they basically crave against the UN well
when unpleasant feeling arises the only
way that they know how to deal with it
is by getting pleasure but sensual
pleasure yeah so
then you can you can be sure then that
any well that's a that's a good point
any pleasure that comes kind of in place
of the suffering to replace it that is
sensal pleasure even if it's not the
pleasure of specific course uh sight
sound smells taste and touches the
pleasure of let's say a concentration
practice that people will be doing the
fact that it comes in place of the
suffering it kind of steals the space
from it so that it can't be there yeah
that is the principle of ensal pleasure
like covering it up yeah so when that's
understood when when desire for sensual
pleasure is seen as basically the only
way the ordinary person knows to deals
with his suffering IE he's not dealing
with it on the right level then by not
engaging with that and by not covering
it up with the methods and techniques
you were just explaining as well what
comes into sight is that underlying
suffering which was there the whole time
already yeah so that's the point it's
it's important when you do that when you
start uh coming into contact with or or
familiarizing yourself with that
liability to suffering that was already
there that you don't develop a view that
um it's because of the practice that
this is happening it's because of your
resistance really to that the unpleasant
feeling that has revealed itself that's
why it's painful not because in and of
itself like this restraint is always
going to be you know this this uh in
fact that's why that's that's many of
the many of the times that's why people
develop a kind of view of nibana being
a almost mystical magical State because
that's the only thing that can
compensate for again replacing the
pleasure of uh that the pain that you
might have taken through renunciation
you need something else now to kind of
down the line come in place of it yeah
and it also covers over that it is
because of one's own actions acting out
of GRE hated and illusion that Nana
isn't realized yeah exactly so that's
the thing then you also realize that
that suffering is there not because of
uh some Cosmic condition that is not
going in your favor it's there it like
you're responsible for it that's why
that and and at the same time that is
the um the um the
[Music]
the positive let's say aspect of it is
that it might seem very Bleak like oh
suffering suffering but the the good
news is you are entirely responsible for
it in the beginning you don't understand
why it's happening it feels like it's
coming by itself but you understand that
that suffering is entirely because of
your mental attitude which is why it can
end as well yeah yeah the mental
attitude that you don't yet see but but
you will never get to see it if you
don't withdraw yourself from the things
that uh again from these Immediate
Solutions yeah so in the beginning if
someone is understanding this widely and
they go about it widely experientially
it might look like their suffering
increases yeah but this needs to be
understood as not necessarily a bad
thing if it's against the right
understanding yeah yeah exactly so the
the the rule of th there would be you make
the rule of th there would be you make
sure that if your mental displeasure is
increasing that it's not because you're
actively seeking it out and trying to
torture yourself but because you are
like you're simply refraining from
covering it up you're simply uh just
seeing what was already there on account
of you not doing certain things it's not
that you're trying to you know um get
yourself well up on purpose or something
yeah and so what commonly happens if
this is not understood like someone
might have been practicing in Lay life
for example certain meditation methods
techniques concentration practices they
become inspired want to become a monk MH
take on the patim Moka training rules
227 training rules that from the day
that you are biku you have to keep them
and for quite a few months or years
whatever they thought their practice was
is this going to be a big mess because
they have a lot of Doubt did I break
this precept did I do that properly and
so on account of act actually learning
how to operate within the patima
training rules which is the first thing
that you should do as a monk that's
going to reveal the mental displeasure
of having doubts am I now holding these
precepts rightly yeah and and so they
might think well my meditation is going
down the drain but actually what they
thought was meditation
[Music]
now they in recogniz the intentions
behind their actions which is where
practices yeah you see if something as
simple as just not being able to keep
some rules can can um arouse that
suffering means you were already liable
to it even if you have never ordained
and stayed in your perfect uh controlled
lay environment where nobody's telling
you what to do the fact that this ended
up happening means you didn't actually
address those defilements yeah so this
is at best exposing them yeah it's not
that they were not there so that's
that's the thing like you want to be
that's the the Common Thread where you
want to be exposing these liabilities
that's the that's the you want to be as
we discussed in the talk on authenticity
the problem is that the natural way of
living is like how do I recognize these
liabilities the
the least how can I go about that but
you actually have to go against the
grain that's that's the the the attitude
that goes with development of the dama
like going against reg grain means that
like instead of habitually covering up
these liabilities you recognize actually
the only way that I can protect myself
from something rightly is if I know that
it's there that's the only or that is
that is coming or that it's or that it
could come yeah if like you can you can
you know uh there's going to be an
earthquake and you just well the same
the same thing like cancer earthquake
whatever um any sort of thing that might
arouse fear or displeasure in your mind
you can either prioritize right now
feeling good and ignoring that it could
happen or you could see that that
liability as a chance to develop
yourself even before it comes so that's
the the whole thing with sickness aging
and death it's not that you kind of um
find something that some special
strategy that will protect you when they
those things come you actually develop
yourself right now by recognizing the
that displeasure and then when those
things come you won't be moved by that
displeasure yeah and so what is then the
right development for someone who
recognizes that old age sickness death
is coming their way that that they are
liable to it
not that it could happen but that it is
going to happen it's just a question of
time yeah and and as said there's that
the Buddha told that King imagine that
there's four great mountains approaching
you from one from the north one from the
south one from the East and one from the
west and you have no way to run and
basically that's birth uh sickness aging
and death and then um that is the sort
of recognition that
can like just having that recognition is
already quite being able to keep that
context in your mind is already
significant progress like from the
starting point of the average person so
once you um once you start recognizing
that you also need to see that
um well unless you have developed virtue
sensor straint and all these requisit
beforehand uh going too far into it
reflecting on it pondering on it too
much uh might probably result in you
know quite unpleasant uh consequences
because you are not like the only when
you happen to had at least some Taste of
the um ease of giving things up of
actual renunciation
yeah you don't know anything else and so
it's like this thing is crushing you and
the only
um satisfaction that you know is outside
of those mountains that are crushing you
so then uh yeah so practically speaking
you won't be able to keep your sanity
yeah and uh contemplate sickness aging
and death fully properly and accurately
unless you have developed that that
criteria of virtue either you will not
be seeing it properly at all and it will
just be an abstract philosophical idea
that doesn't change your life at all
yeah or you might be doing it properly
but then it will have some uh edgy uh
because exactly because if somebody's
going to think uh you see having been it
if somebody's going to realize having
been born I am ADV once old enough to
die so it's not birth and then death and
then my life sort of in in the in the
middle no being here means right now I
am liable to old age sickness death
that's the immediacy of birth of AE
sickness death then what is the point of
of building up anything and making
myself more dependent on Acquisitions on
things in the world if at any moment
beyond my control that can be taken away
from me yeah right so rather than um
learning how to be with the breath for
30 seconds rather than 20 or for a few
minutes rather than one um people would
be coming closer to what the Buddha was
teaching by asking themselves
what am I practically doing in my life
and am I building up attachments and
Acquisitions which means that when they
are going to be taken away from me it's
going to be more painful and I know
right now if I'm honest and quiet and on
my own that anxiety in the back of my
mind like oh stuff had better not start
happening now because I'm still fully
dependent on those things and that is
the actual daoka that people don't want
to experience the irony is that how to
not experience that anxiety most of the
time is by Sur is by building up more
Acquisitions in order to distract
yourself from it which actually then
aggravates the problem so you get caught
up in this circle which is a vicious one
and as long as that's not understood
your whole situation basically
deteriorates which is the exact opposite
of the real development yeah and and uh
that's one good point like you have to
recognize that you can't get around the
fact that suffering depends on
acquisition that's it as it s to say so
that's that's something that people have
to hammer in especially these days
because there's the idea that you know
you can have your cake and eat it too if
you just find the perfect method you can
have your Acquisitions and you know
dance away from the suffering at the
same time maneuver around it but the
thing is um suffering is like you can
find a you can find a
good technique to outrun it but but the
thing is you are creating it in the
first place out of those Acquisitions
and all all of those things will
eventually have to fail at some point
doesn't matter how much it works right
now yeah and those Acquisitions will be
factually increasing at at the very
least at the time of death or when
things really start going wrong um that
will increase the intensity of of how
much that's going to hit you and then
when uh you know you're against the wall
you don't have anywhere to run then
you're going to see oh actually the only
way to to
truly not end up this way was to not
build up these things in the first place
and but then then it's going to be too
late yeah then it's too late and also we
should perhaps I'm not sure if this is
where we want to go with the discussion
now but Acquisitions people might think
well that is just material things like a
car a house or
but actually in the context of that's
not wrong as such you have to start yeah
you have to start on that level but
actually Acquisitions is regarding the
five acus as mine yeah but see that's
the fundamental level of giving up
acquisition yeah but see the point is
like when you emphasize that level too
much people would think okay no no but
then the the I can still keep the the
house and the I I just have to give it
the five Aggregates so in a yeah so we
should start by recognizing that that
there is also mundane Acquisitions and
you want to create some basic order in
your life there which means basically
less is more yeah I mean it's a popular
phrase but it's not wrong in this
context and from there you you create
the space and the mental energy as well
to find the actual let's say fundamental
level where the where the reflection of
dhama takes place yeah the thing is like
without giving up those things giving up
those things in of themselves doesn't
mean you have understood acquisition
that's it yeah but there's no way that
you will understand what acquisition is
without giving up those you have to like
dig through the it's like soil kind of
on top of like if you talk about the
five Aggregates being the base like you
still have to kind of dig down to it by
you know giving up the kind of more
mundane things yeah yeah so the five
Aggregates whatever you might think the
five Aggregates
are while you're
still engaging with the secondary
results of the five args which is sense
objects mhm you like it's it's well I
mean people see the five arates as sense
objects that's like the most perverse
egregious thing that but but it it does
happen that way because it didn't
cultivate that prerequisite of of of
actually like your understanding of the
five Aggregates even if you have no uh
theoretical information about the dma
and these mystical insights of you know
things constantly changing or something
your understanding the five Aggregates
is more accurate if you're restrained
than if you're not and and and like then
if you're not restrained and then
watching all these mystical uh you know
revelations in your meditation actually
yeah and those mystical Revelations have
already nothing to do with it anyway
just to be clear yeah of course but it's
it's uh it can be quite distracting
because it it like you know it's the
novelty of it and and and all that but
all all you have to fundamentally ask
yourself is am I sure that when sickness
aging and death come that this is
actually freeing me from that or is it
just providing me some form of
entertainment that's taking me away from
that so yeah that or or is it just
giving me a way to pretend that sickness
aging and death don't exist because it's
just these particles constantly changing
or something and there I I don't suffer
which is going back to that discussion
we had about not denying the
significance of
things yeah so all of that like if you if you
yeah so all of that like if you if you
haven't been able to develop these
precepts and and and
prerequisites all the the insights you
might be developing about Ana anata all
these things they will come through that
container of wrong view of denying ing
the the fact that things are real
denying the fact that there is Choice
that's why you would end up with these
ideas that all my you know it's it's
just determinism because because you
know it's one moment conditioning the
next and therefore I have no choice
because everything is just this constant
process so you end up just denying
things again to to find a shortcut to
free yourself from that suffering yeah
all this is just a dream illusion if my
ignorance is dispelled I will I will
discover the what is really really real
which is some sort of ultimate
nothingness behind the scene where where
sickness aging and death can't go can't
go supposedly but um yeah if that's
somebody's background view which is
actually what mysticism is this
distinction between appearance then
inadvertently somebody will be
cultivating ill will because things are
there but if you assume that they
shouldn't be there because you think
they're only there on account of
ignorance and when the ignorance is
dispelled you will see what things
really are namely nothing then you sit
there and you realize well things are
still there I must be doing it wrong and
you just keep working yourself up
factually cultivating ill will rather
than actually recognizing that things
being there was never the problem and I
mean the thing is it might genuinely
work like it might get to Advanced
stages whatever but the thing is all of
it remains within the container
of uh did you actually address sickness
aging and death or did you just kind of
took a like a detour to somewhere else
yeah so then fundamentally did not yeah
yeah exactly so um it's it's the the
the fundamentally the resistance to
suffering is the problem it's not that
you don't see the
[Music] um but it could be um yeah
um but it could be um yeah
so um you could say the resistance isn't
the problem that's the whole point
resistance of resistance is the problem
yeah sure so so it's it's
um
yeser sorry yeah yeah so you start from
the position of resistance oh yeah so so
it's seeing that and and not seeing that
as Pro problematic yes seeing seeing
that the thing the fact that things are
unpleasant yeah is in and of itself not
the problem yeah so that's why the
better had unpleasant experiences and he
didn't have a choice of aversion towards
them yeah so that's the that's the um
the distinction like you recognize
weights yes I'm suffering a kind of
unpleasant feeling but that's not that's
not the fault of the unpleasant feeling
it's the fault of my lack of
understanding in regard to it and you
just keep that perspective and then
um at least you won't be able to go too
far into uh thinking that unpleasant
feeling is a problem in and of
itself so and it it doesn't matter where
it comes from it doesn't matter if it's
bodily pain of uh you know uring heat
cold um elements and stuff or if it's uh
mental displeasure of the um confinement
that results from from restraining your
bodily Behavior your verbal behavior and
your mental behavior all the displeasure
that comes from that none of it in and
of itself is a problem that's why um the
S the the second Noble Truth is craving
is the root of suffering not suffering
is the root of suffering MH so it
doesn't matter what feeling it is that's
why that it says uh any feeling whether
it's past or future high or low inferior
Superior uh it doesn't matter where it
came from all of it has to be understood
in the same way and that's how as you
said before you go through it you don't
get rid of it you don't explain it you
don't uh hide from it you
just abandon your wrong attitude in
regard to it and while the Thing Remains
the Same you free yourself from it and
then you don't need to manage anything
and then the most intense displeasure
displeasure like a mountain not that the
mountain of sickness aging and death
changed and you turn it into something
else and that's why it doesn't suffer
you don't suffer no it's still the same
Mountain but uh it doesn't affect you
anymore that's a big difference yeah
I thought we could also mention
um what is it that
uh reveals that suffering that you need
to
learn to U not try to get rid of
immediately it's not that uh having not
changed your way of existing in the world you
your way of existing in the world you
just start thinking about your liability
to suffering because that's not going to
be accurate
uh there has to be some practical giving
up that actually exposes that uh
discrepancy between the place where your
mind is the expectations that it
has and the fundamental uncertainty of
the world so there has to be some
factual renunciation for you to start to
see that suffering not just like I keep
living the same way and I just reflect
on these truths because any philosopher
can do that really it's not a what makes
it actually a practice that's developing
your mind is when you practically live
according to um the recognition that at
least taking it on faith that um certain
things that you do are making the
suffering worse so restraining
yourself uh first in regard to the
body in regard to the speech in regard
to your
mind but most importantly those first
two as as a as a starting point
um naturally the suffering will you
don't even need to look for it like even
if you're not reflecting on it if you
have been living like 99% of people
today uh that that suffering will start
to reveal itself the suffering again
that you're not looking for it's it's
going to be visible and evidence just on
account of you not doing something and
actually that's already a red flag like
telling you revealing to you that this
that there's a problem here if I need to
keep doing these things which
fundamentally I might not be able to do
if my environment changes if if um my
access to these things changes that's
already a red flag that there's a
dependence there and that's
fundamentally that is what the suffering
is is that liability to displeasure when
you don't get things the way you want
it's not like I'm free from suffering
just in the present because I happen to
have the right circumstances the
suffering is there even if everything
goes well
because it could not go well yeah that
is the that's also the definition in
quite a few discourses of what is the
original suffering having to put up with
things that you do not want and not
getting the things that you want yeah
and then it says in short the five
holding Aggregates are what they
suffering then it Dives all the way to
the to the Aggregates um so so you are
practically saying that if people are
hearing this and they say well
everything is going okay but is Mon's
talking about suffering and so on well
start keeping the a precepts not just
for a weekend or for a month but um have
to view that you know I'm going to give
this up for the rest of my life because
that's how you're going to feel the
weight of it yeah H and then you can see
how there is this sort of Habitual
momentum which might not be immediately
apparent but stick to it and it will be
there and then there is the choice am am I now
and then there is the choice am am I now
going to keep those precepts which means
I have to resist some tendency that I
never saw before because I was always
running with it that is how two car for
most people will practically begin to
show its face so to speak that's a good
point like you can't just take it on for
if you want to really start recognizing
that suffering so that you can
understand it you can't just take it up
uh temporarily
because it's like uh well any drug
addict can give up his drug for a
weekend and he knows he's going to have
it in the end if he get he if he has a
good enough alternative sensual motivation
enough alternative sensual motivation
like you know he has to go to a job
interview or something he can he can
give up his his drug no problem so you
will only really start feeling it even I
mean literally with the case of drug
addict like when he tells himself no I'm
never going to have this again but
anybody can do them for like two weeks
one month two months that doesn't mean
much and also if one wants to start
thinking about death rightly then this
is how you start by giving things up in
in the sense I am never going to do this
again and that weight is experientially
what death will be for you not your
ideas like well when I'm that I'm not
there therefore death is no longer a
problem and all these kind of abstract
personalizations which quite miss the
mark start to create some basic order in
your life I.E align with the eight
precepts and then there will be experientially a
and then there will be experientially a
foundation for you to sort of get the
feeling but in a non-sentimental sense
of what death actually is you will get
in contact with your feelings literally
by keeping the precepts not by you know
doing some sort of a new age practice
yeah you will start to see your feelings
on the right level just by doing that
and you actually mentioned it like uh
that the that formulation of the first
Noble Truth that ends with the five
aggregates saying like the fundamental suffering is
saying like the fundamental suffering is
the five Aggregates and it gives that as
a kind of a summary of the things that
pred it so it's precisely by exposing
yourself to these things that you would
necessarily want to to see in the
beginning like the fact that you're
liable to contact with things that you
don't want to be in contact with liable
to not be in contact with things that
you do want to be in contact with that's
why that's the first level to the the
the origin is the craving yeah so then
by by ironically
that's the route where through which you
will get to see the five Aggregates not
by like keeping staying in your
comfortable environment and then
thinking what are the five agregates so
um and then writing a PhD about it and
that's why then so even death like you
won't be able
to practically reflect on what death is
unless you have taken on some amount of
uh that self-discipline and in terms of
the precepts in terms of sity because uh
like denunciation you could say it's a
form of uh losing things before they are
taken away from you yeah and then you
lose things so as to
practice and to develop your mind in
regard to loss before it even comes
that's the principle of
renunciation so you don't wait until it
gets ripped away from you and it was
like already so encrusted and it beded
into your hand that it rips your whole
hand off with it yeah you actually take
it off while it's still only a little
bit sticky and then you develop yourself
so that you can you never take it off
yeah that's the Sy like a hot iron ball
and it falls in your hand and you just
drop it because you actually but but you
need to experience it as hot and as
burning and see the whole problem is all
these actions and all these uh you know
unrestrained behavior and then the whole
psychologization and techniques and and
management methods that come on top of
it are all directed and not Fe feeling
the heat of that ball while you're
holding it yeah